Adventure II. of Siegfried

In the Netherlands there grew the child of a noble king (his father had for name Siegmund,[1] his mother Siegelind),[2] in a mighty castle, known far and wide, in the lowlands of the Rhine: Xanten,[3] men called it. Of this hero I sing, how fair he grew. Free he was of every blemish. Strong and famous he later became, this valiant man. Ho! What great worship he won in this world! Siegfried hight this good and doughty knight. Full many kingdoms did he put to the test through his warlike mood. Through his strength of body he rode into many lands. Ho! What bold warriors he after found in the Burgundian land! Mickle wonders might one tell of Siegfried in his prime, in youthful days; what honors he received and how fair of body he. The most stately women held him in their love; with the zeal which was his due men trained him. But of himself what virtues he attained! Truly his father’s lands were honored, that he was found in all things of such right lordly mind. Now was he become of the age that he might ride to court. Gladly the people saw him, many a maid wished that his desire might ever bear him hither. Enow gazed on him with favor; of this the prince was well aware. Full seldom was the youth allowed to ride without a guard of knights. Siegmund and Siegelind bade deck him out in brave attire. The older knights who were acquaint with courtly custom, had him in their care. Well therefore might he win both folk and land.

Now he was of the strength that he bare weapons well. Whatever he needed thereto, of this he had enow. With purpose he began to woo fair ladies; these bold Siegfried courted well in proper wise. Then bade Siegmund have cried to all his men, that he would hold a feasting with his loving kindred. The tidings thereof men brought into the lands of other kings. To the strangers and the home-folk he gave steeds and armor. Wheresoever any was found who, because of his birth, should become a knight, these noble youths were summoned to the land for the feasting. Here with the youthful prince they gained the knightly sword. Wonders might one tell of this great feast; Siegmund and Siegelind wist well how to gain great worship with their gifts, of which their hands dealt out great store. Wherefore one beheld many strangers riding to their realm. Four hundred sword-thanes[4] were to put on knightly garb with Siegfried. Many a fair maid was aught but idle with the work, for he was beloved of them all. Many precious stones the ladies inlaid on the gold, which together with the edging they would work upon the dress of the proud young warriors, for this must needs be done.

The host bade make benches for the many valiant men, for the midsummer festival,[5] at which Siegfried should gain the name of knight. Then full many a noble knight and many a high-born squire did hie them to the minster. Right were the elders in that they served the young, as had been done to them afore. Pastimes they had and hope of much good cheer. To the honor of God a mass was sung; then there rose from the people full great a press, as the youths were made knights in courtly wise, with such great honors as might not ever lightly be again. Then they ran to where they found saddled many a steed. In Siegmund’s court the hurtling[6] waxed so fierce that both palace[7] and hall were heard to ring; the high-mettled warriors clashed with mighty sound. From young and old one heard many a shock, so that the splintering of the shafts reëchoed to the clouds. Truncheons[8] were seen flying out before the palace from the hand of many a knight. This was done with zeal. At length the host bade cease the tourney and the steeds were led away. Upon the turf one saw all to-shivered[9] many a mighty buckler and great store of precious stones from the bright spangles[10] of the shields. Through the hurtling this did hap.

Then the guests of the host betook them to where men bade them sit. With good cheer they refreshed them and with the very best of wine, of which one bare frill plenty. To the strangers and the home-folk was shown worship enow. Though much pastime they had throughout the day, many of the strolling folk forsware all rest. They served for the largess, which men found there richly, whereby Siegmund’s whole land was decked with praise. Then bade the king enfeoff Siegfried, the youth, with land and castles, as he himself had done. Much his hand bestowed upon the sword-companions. The journey liked them well, that to this land they were come. The feasting lasted until the seventh day. Siegelind, the noble queen, for the love of her son, dealt out ruddy gold in time-honored wise. Full well she wot how to make him beloved of the folk. Scarce could a poor man be found among the strolling mimes. Steeds and raiment were scattered by their hand, as if they were to live not one more day. I trow that never did serving folk use such great bounty. With worshipful honors the company departed hence. Of the mighty barons the tale doth tell that they desired the youth unto their lord, but of this the stately knight, Sir Siegfried, listed naught. Forasmuch as both Siegmund and Siegelind were still alive, the dear child of them twain wished not to wear a crown, but fain would he become a lord against all the deeds of force within his lands, whereof the bold and daring knight was sore adread.

Adventure XXXVII. How Margrave Rüdeger Was Slain

The strangers had done full well at dawn. Meanwhile Gotelind’s husband came to court. Bitterly faithful Rüdeger wept when he saw the grievous wounds on either side. “Woe is me,” quoth the champion, “that I was ever born, sith none may stay this mickle grief! However fain I would make for peace, the king will not consent, for he seeth ever more and more the sufferings of his men.”

Then the good Knight Rüdeger sent to Dietrich, if perchance they might turn the fate of the high-born kings. The king of Berne sent answer: “Who might now forfend? King Etzel will let none part the strife.”

Then a Hunnish warrior, that saw Rüdeger stand with weeping eyes, and many tears had he shed, spake to the queen: “Now behold how he doth stand, that hath the greatest power at Etzel’s court and whom both lands and people serve. Why have so many castles been given to Rüdeger, of which he doth hold such store from the king in fief? Not one sturdy stroke hath he dealt in all this strife. Bethinks, he recketh not how it fare here at court, sith he hath his will in full. Men say of him, he be bolder than any other wight. Little hath that been seen in these parlous[1] days.”

Sad in heart the faithful vassal gazed at him whom he heard thus speak. Him-thought: “Thou shalt pay for this. Thou sayest, I be a craven, and hast told thy tale too loud at court.”

His fist he clenched, then ran he at him and smote the Hunnish man so mightily that he lay dead at his feet full soon. Through this King Etzel’s woe grew greater.

“Away, thou arrant coward,” cried Rüdeger, “forsooth I have enow of grief and pain. How dost thou taunt me, that I fight not here? Certes, I have good cause to hate the strangers, and would have done all in my power against them, had I not led the warriors hither. Of a truth I was their safeguard to my master’s land. Therefore the hand of me, wretched man, may not strive against them.”

Then spake Etzel, the noble king, to the margrave: “How have ye helped us, most noble Rüdeger! We have so many fey[2] in the land, that we have no need of more. Full evil have ye done.”

At this the noble knight made answer: “Forsooth he grieved my mood and twitted me with the honors and the goods, such store of which I have received from thy hand. This hath cost the liar dear.”

The queen, too, was come and had seen what fortuned to the Huns through the hero’s wrath. Passing sore she bewailed it; her eyes grew moist as she spake to Rüdeger: “How have we deserved that ye should increase the sorrows of the king and me? Hitherto ye have told us, that for our sake ye would risk both life and honor. I heard full many warriors accord to you the palm. Let me mind you of your fealty and that ye swore, when that ye counseled me to Etzel, good knight and true, that ye would serve me till one of us should die. Never have I, poor woman, had such great need of this.”

“There’s no denying that I swore to you, my lady, for your sake I’d risk both life and honor, but I did not swear that I would lose my soul. ’Twas I that bade the high-born lordings to this feast.”

Quoth she: “Bethink thee, Rüdeger, of thy great fealty, of thy constancy, and of thine oaths, that thou wouldst ever avenge mine injuries and all my woes.”

Said the margrave: “Seldom have I denied you aught.”

Mighty Etzel, too, began implore; upon their knees they sank before the knight. Men saw the noble margrave stand full sad. Pitifully the faithful warrior spake: “Woe is me, most wretched man, that I have lived to see this day. I must give over all my honors, my fealty, and my courtesie, that God did bid me use. Alas, great God of heaven, that death will not turn this from me! I shall act basely and full evil, whatever I do or leave undone. But if I give over both, then will all people blame me. Now may he advise me, who hath given me life.”

Still the king and the queen, too, begged unceasingly. Through this warriors must needs thereafter lose their lives at Rüdeger’s hands, when the hero also died. Ye may well hear it now, that he deported him full pitifully. He wist that it would bring him scathe and monstrous woe. Gladly would he have refused the king and queen. He feared full sore that if he slew but one of the strangers, the world would bear him hate.

Then the brave man addressed him to the king: “Sir King, take back again all that I have from you, my land with its castles, let not a whit remain to me. On foot will I wander into other lands.”

At this King Etzel spake: “Who else should help me then? I’ll give thee the land and all its castles, as thine own, that thou mayst avenge me on my foes. Thou shalt be a mighty king at Etzel’s side.”

Then answered Rüdeger: “How shall I do this deed? I bade them to my house and home; in friendly wise I offered them both food and drink and gave them gifts. How may I counsel their death? People will lightly ween, that I be craven. No service of mine have I refused these noble lordings and their men. Now I rue the kinship I have gained with them. I gave my daughter to Giselher, the knight; to none in all the world could she have been better given, for courtesie and honor, for fealty and wealth. Never have I seen so young a prince of such right courteous mind.”

Then Kriemhild spake again: “Most noble Rüdeger, take pity on our griefs, on mine and on the king’s. Bethink thee well, that king did never gain such baneful guests.”

To the noble dame the margrave spake: “Rüdeger’s life must pay to-day for whatsoever favors ye and my lord have shown me. Therefore must I die; no longer may it be deferred. I know full well, that my castles and my lands will be voided for you to-day through the hand of one of these men. To your mercy I commend my wife and children and the strangers[3] who be at Bechelaren.”

“Now God requite thee, Rüdeger,” spake the king, and both he and the queen grew glad. “Thy people shall be well commended to our care. For mine own weal I trust thou too shalt go unscathed.”

Etzel’s bride began to weep. Then body and soul he staked upon the venture. He spake: “I must perform what I have vowed. Alas for my friends, whom I am loth to fight.”

Men saw him go sadly from the presence of the king. Close at hand he found his warriors standing. He spake: “Ye must arm you all, my men, for, alas, I must needs encounter the bold Burgundians.”

They bade the squires run nimbly to where lay their arms. Whether it were helm or buckler, ’twas all brought forth to them by their meiny. Later the proud strangers heard told baleful tales. Rüdeger was now armed, and with him five hundred men; thereto he gained twelve champions, who would fain win renown in the stress of battle. They wist not that death drew nigh them. Then Rüdeger was seen to march with helmet donned. The margrave’s men bare keen-edged swords, and their bright shields and broad upon their arms. This the fiddler saw; greatly he rued the sight. When young Giselher beheld his lady’s father walk with his helm upon his head, how might he know what he meant thereby, save that it portended good? Therefore the noble prince waxed passing merry of mood.

“Now well is me of such kinsmen,” spake Knight Giselher, “whom we have won upon this journey; from my wife we shall reap much profit here. Lief it is to me, that this betrothal hath taken place.”

“I know not whence ye take your comfort,” spake then the minstrel; “when have ye seen so many heroes walk with helmets donned and swords in hand, for the sake of peace? Rüdeger doth think to win his castles and his lands in fight with us.”

Or ever the fiddler had ended his speech, men saw the noble Rüdeger before the house. At his feet he placed his trusty shield, and now both service and greeting he must needs refuse his friends. Into the hall the noble margrave called: “Ye doughty Nibelungs, now guard you well on every side. Ye were to profit by me, now I shall bring you scathe. Aforetime we were friends, but of this troth I now would fain be rid.”

The hard-pressed men were startled at this tale, for none gained aught of joy, that he whom they did love would now fain fight them. From their foes they had already suffered mickle stress of war. “Now God of heaven forbid,” spake Gunther, the knight, “that ye should give over your love of us and your great fealty, on which we counted of a truth. Better things I trow of you, than that ye should ever do this deed.”

“Alas, I cannot give it over, but must fight you, for I have vowed it. Now ward you, brave heroes, and ye love your life. King Etzel’s wife would not release me from mine oath.”

“Ye declare this feud too late,” spake the high-born king. “Now may God requite you, most noble Rüdeger, for all the love and fealty that ye have shown us, if ye would only act more kindly at the end. I and my kinsmen, we ought ever to serve you for the noble gifts ye gave us, when ye brought us hither faithfully to Etzel’s land. Now, noble Rüdeger, think on this.”

“How gladly would I grant you,” spake Knight Rüdeger, “that I might weigh out my gifts for you with full measure, as willingly as I had hoped, if I never should be blamed on that account.”

“Turn back, noble Rüdeger,” spake then Gernot, “for host did never give his guests such loving cheer as ye did us. This shall profit you well, and we remain alive.”

“Would to God,” spake Rüdeger, “most noble Gernot, that ye were on the Rhine and I were dead with passing honor, sith I must now encounter you! Never did friends act worse to heroes.”

“Now God requite you, Sir Rüdeger,” answered Gernot, “for your passing rich gifts. Your death doth rue me, if such knightly virtues shall be lost with you. Here I bear your sword that ye gave me, good knight and true. It hath never failed me in all this need. Many a knight fell dead beneath its edges. It is bright and steady, glorious and good; nevermore, I ween, will warrior give so rich a gift. And will ye not turn back, but come to meet us, and slay aught of the friends I still have here, with your own sword will I take your life. Then will ye rue me, Rüdeger, ye and your high-born wife.”

“Would to God, Sir Gernot, that this might come to pass, that all your will might here be done, and that your kinsmen escaped unscathed! Then both my daughter and my wife may trust you well, forsooth.”

Then of the Burgundians there spake fair Uta’s son: “Why do ye so, Sir Rüdeger? Those that be come with us, do all like you well. Ye encounter us in evil wise; ye wish to make your fair daughter a widow far too soon. If ye and your warriors match me now with strife, how right unkindly do ye let it appear, that I trust you well above all other men and therefore won me your daughter to wife.”

“Think on your fealty, most noble and high-born king. And God let you escape,” so spake Rüdeger, “let the maiden suffer not for me. For your own virtue’s sake, vouchsafe her mercy.”

“That I should do by right,” spake the youthful Giselher, “but if my noble kinsmen here within must die through you, then my steadfast friendship for you and for your daughter must be parted.”

“Now may God have mercy on us,” answered the valiant man. Then they raised their shields, as though they would hence to fight the guests in Kriemhild’s hall, but Hagen cried full loud adown the steps. “Pray tarry awhile, most noble Rüdeger,” so spake Hagen; “I and my lords would fain have further parley, as doth befit our need. What can the death of us wanderers avail King Etzel? I stand here in a fearful plight; the shield that Lady Gotelind gave me to bear hath been cut to pieces by the Huns. I brought it with friendly purpose into Etzel’s land. O that God in heaven would grant, that I might bear so good a shield as that thou hast in thy hand, most noble Rüdeger! Then I should no longer need a hauberk in the fray.”

“Gladly would I serve thee with my shield, durst I offer it before Kriemhild. Yet take it, Hagen, and bear it on thine arm. Ho, if thou couldst only wield it in the Burgundian land!”

When he so willingly offered to give the shield, enow of eyes grew red with scalding tears. ‘T was the last gift that ever Rüdeger of Bechelaren gave to any knight. However fierce Hagen, and however stern of mood, the gift did touch him, which the good hero, so near to death, had given. Many a noble knight gan mourn with him.

“Now God in heaven requite you, most noble Rüdeger. Your like will nevermore be found, who giveth homeless warriors such lordly gifts. God grant that your courtesie may ever live.” Again Hagen spake: “Woe is me of these tales, we had so many other griefs to bear. Let complaint be made to heaven, if we must fight with friends.”

Quoth the margrave: “Inly doth this grieve me.”

“Now God requite you, for the gift, most noble Rüdeger. Howso these high-born warriors deport them toward you, my hand shall never touch you in the fight, and ye slew them all from the Burgundian land.”

Courteously the good Sir Rüdeger bowed him low. On every side they wept, that none might soothe this pain of heart. That was a mighty grief. In Rüdeger would die the father of all knightly virtues.

Then Folker, the minstrel, spake from out the hall: “Sith my comrade Hagen hath made his peace with you, ye shall have it just as steadfastly from my hand, for well ye earned it, when we came into this land. Most noble margrave, ye shall be mine envoy, too. The margravine gave me these ruddy arm rings, that I should wear them here at the feasting. These ye may yourself behold, that ye may later be my witness.”

“Now God of heaven grant,” spake Rüdeger, “that the margravine may give you more! I’ll gladly tell these tales to my dear love, if I see her in health again. Of this ye shall not doubt.”

When he had vowed him this, Rüdeger raised high his shield. No longer he bided, but with raging mood, like a berserker, he rushed upon the guests. Many a furious blow the noble margrave struck. The twain, Folker and Hagen, stepped further back, as they had vowed to him afore. Still he found standing by the tower such valiant men, that Rüdeger began the fight with anxious doubts. With murderous intent Gunther and Gernot let him in, good heroes they! Giselher stood further back, which irked him sore, in truth. He voided Rüdeger, for still he had hope of life. Then the margrave’s men rushed at their foes; in knightly wise one saw them follow their lord. In their hands they bare their keen-edged swords, the which cleft there many a helm and lordly shield. The tired warriors dealt the men of Bechelaren many a mighty blow, that cut smooth and deep through the shining mail, down to the very quick.

Rüdeger’s noble fellowship was now come quite within. Into the fight Folker and Hagen sprang anon. They gave no quarter, save to one man alone. Through the hands of the twain the blood streamed down from the helmets. How grimly rang the many swords within! The shield plates sprang from their fastenings, and the precious stones, cut from the shields, fell down into the gore. So grimly they fought, that men will never do the like again. The lord of Bechelaren raged to and fro, as one who wotteth how to use great prowess in the fray. Passing like to a worshipful champion and a bold did Rüdeger bear him on that day. Here stood the warriors, Gunther and Gernot, and smote many a hero dead in the fray. Giselher and Dankwart, the twain, recked so little, that they brought full many a knight to his last day of life. Full well did Rüdeger make appear that he was strong enow, brave and well-armed. Ho, what knights he slew! This a Burgundian espied; perforce it angered him, and thus Sir Rüdeger’s death drew near.

The stalwart Gernot accosted the hero; to the margrave he spake: “It appeareth, ye will not leave my men alive, most noble Rüdeger. That irketh me beyond all measure, no longer can I bear the sight. So may your present work you harm, sith ye have taken from me such store of friends. Pray address you unto me, most noble man and brave, your gift shall be paid for as best I can.”

Or ever the margrave could reach his foe, bright armor rings must needs grow dull with blood. Then at each other sprang these honor-seeking men. Either gan guard him against mighty wounds. So sharp were their swords, that naught might avail against them. Then Rüdeger, the knight, smote Gernot a buffet through his helmet, the which was as hard as flint, so that the blood gushed forth. But this the bold knight and good repaid eftsoon. High in his hand he now poised Rüdeger’s gift, and though wounded unto death, he smote him a stroke through his good and trusty shield down to his helmet band. And so fair Gotelind’s husband was done to death. Certes, so rich a gift was never worse repaid. So fell alike both Gernot and Rüdeger, slain in the fray, through each other’s hand.

Then first waxed Hagen wroth, when he saw the monstrous scathe. Quoth the hero of Troneg: “Evil hath it fared with us. In these two men we have taken a loss so great that neither their land nor people will e’er recover from the blow. Rüdeger’s champions must answer to us homeless men.”

“Alas for my brother, who hath here been done to death. What evil tales I hear all time! Noble Rüdeger, too, must ever rue me. The loss and the grievous wounds are felt on either side.”

When Lord Giselher saw his betrothed’s father dead, those within the hall were forced to suffer need. Fiercely death sought his fellowship; not one of those of Bechelaren escaped with life. Gunther and Giselher and Hagen, too, Dankwart and Folker, the right good knights, went to where they found the two men lying. Then by these heroes tears of grief were shed.

“Death doth sorely rob us,” spake Giselher, the youth. “Now give over your weeping and go we bite the breeze, that the mailed armor of us storm-weary men may cool. Certes, I ween, that God in heaven vouchsafeth us no more to live.”

This champion was seen to sit and that to lean against the wall, but all again were idle. Rüdeger’s heroes lay still in death. The din had died away; the hush endured so long, it vexed King Etzel.

“Alack for such services,” spake the queen. “They be not so true, that our foes must pay with their life at Rüdeger’s hands. I trow, he doth wish to lead them back to the Burgundian land. What booteth it, King Etzel, that we have given him whatso he would? The knight hath done amiss, he who should avenge us, doth make his peace.”

To this Folker, the full dapper knight, made answer: “This is not true, alas, most noble queen. Durst I give the lie to such a high-born dame, then had ye most foully lied against Rüdeger. He and his champions be cozened in this peace. So eagerly he did what the king commanded, that he and all his fellowship lie here in death. Now look around you, Kriemhild, to see whom ye may now command. The good Knight Rüdeger hath served you to his end. And ye will not believe the tale, we’ll let you see.”

To their great grief ’twas done; they bare the slain hero to where the king might see him. Never had there happed to Etzel’s men a grief so great. When they saw the margrave borne forth dead, no scribe might write or tell the frantic grief of men and women, which there gan show itself from dole of heart. King Etzel’s sorrow waxed so great that the mighty king did voice his woe of heart, as with a lion’s roar. Likewise did his queen. Beyond all measure they bewailed the good Knight Rüdeger’s death.

Adventure I[2]

Full many a wonder is told us in stories old, of heroes worthy of praise, of hardships dire, of joy and feasting, of the fighting of bold warriors, of weeping and of wailing; now ye may hear wonders told.

In Burgundy there grew so noble a maid that in all the lands none fairer might there be. Kriemhild[3] was she called; a comely woman she became, for whose sake many a knight must needs lose his life. Well worth the loving was this winsome maid. Bold knights strove for her, none bare her hate. Her peerless body was beautiful beyond degree; the courtly virtues of this maid of noble birth would have adorned many another woman too.

Three kings, noble and puissant, did nurture her, Gunther[4] and Gernot,[5] warriors worthy of praise, and Giselher,[6] the youth, a chosen knight. This lady was their sister, the princes had her in their care. The lordings were free in giving, of race high-born, passing bold of strength were they, these chosen knights. Their realm hight Burgundy. Great marvels they wrought hereafter in Etzel’s[7] land. At Worms[8] upon the Rhine they dwelt with all their power. Proud knights from out their lands served them with honor, until their end was come. Thereafter they died grievously, through the hate of two noble dames.

Their mother, a mighty queen, was called the Lady Uta,[9] their father, Dankrat,[10] who left them the heritage after his life was over; a mighty man of valor that he was, who won thereto in youth worship full great. These kings, as I have said, were of high prowess. To them owed allegiance the best of warriors, of whom tales were ever told, strong and brave, fearless in the sharp strife. Hagen[11] there was of Troneg, thereto his brother Dankwart,[12] the doughty; Ortwin of Metz;[13] Gere[14] and Eckewart,[15] the margraves twain; Folker of Alzei,[16] endued with fullness of strength. Rumolt[17] was master of the kitchen, a chosen knight; the lords Sindolt and Hunolt, liegemen of these three kings, had rule of the court and of its honors. Thereto had they many a warrior whose name I cannot tell. Dankwart was marshal; his nephew, Ortwin, seneschal unto the king; Sindolt was cupbearer, a chosen knight; Hunolt served as chamberlain; well they wot how to fill these lofty stations. Of the forces of the court and its far-reaching might, of the high worship[18] and of the chivalry these lords did ply with joy throughout their life, of this forsooth none might relate to you the end.

In the midst of these high honors Kriemhild dreamed a dream, of how she trained a falcon, strong, fair, and wild, which, before her very eyes, two eagles rent to pieces. No greater sorrow might chance to her in all this world. This dream then she told to Uta her mother, who could not unfold it to the dutiful maid in better wise than this: “The falcon which thou trainest, that is a noble man, but thou must needs lose him soon, unless so be that God preserve him.”

“Why speakest thou to me of men, dear brother mine? I would fain ever be without a warrior’s love. So fair will I remain until my death, that I shall never gain woe from love of man.”

“Now forswear this not too roundly,” spake the mother in reply. “If ever thou shalt wax glad of heart in this world, that will chance through the love of man. Passing fair wilt thou become, if God grant thee a right worthy knight.”

“I pray you leave this speech,” spake she, “my lady. Full oft hath it been seen in many a wife, how joy may at last end in sorrow. I shall avoid them both, then can it ne’er go ill with me.”

Thus in her heart Kriemhild forsware all love. Many a happy day thereafter the maiden lived without that she wist any whom she would care to love. In after days she became with worship a valiant hero’s bride. He was the selfsame falcon which she beheld in her dream that her mother unfolded to her. How sorely did she avenge this upon her nearest kin, who slew him after! Through his dying alone there fell full many a mother’s son.

Adventure XXI. How Kriemhild Journeyed to the Huns

Let now the messengers ride. We will do you to wit, how the queen journeyed through the lands and where Giselher and Gernot parted from her. They had served her as their fealty bade them. Down to Vergen[1] on the Danube they rode; here they gan crave leave of the queen, for they would ride again to the Rhine. Without tears these faithful kinsmen might not part. Doughty Giselher spake then to his sister: “Whenever, lady, thou shouldst need me, when aught doth trouble thee, let me but know, and I will ride in thy service to Etzel’s land.”

Those who were her kin she kissed upon the mouth. Lovingly they took their leave of Margrave Rüdeger’s men. The queen had with her many a fair-fashioned maid, full a hundred and four, that wore costly robes of rich, gay-colored silks. Many broad shields were borne close by the ladies on the road, but many a lordly warrior turned then from her.

They journeyed soon from thence down through Bavarian land. Here the tale was told that many unknown strangers had gathered there, where still a cloister standeth and where the Inn floweth into the Danube. In the town of Passau, where lived a bishop, lodgings were soon emptied and the prince’s court as well, as they hurried forth to meet the strangers in the Bavarian land, where the Bishop Pilgrim[2] found fair Kriemhild. The knights of the land were little loth, when in her train they saw so many comely maids; with their eyes they courted the daughters of noble knights. Later good lodgings were given the noble guests.

With his niece the bishop rode toward Passau. When it was told the burghers of the town that Kriemhild was come, their prince’s sister’s child, well was she greeted by the merchants. The bishop had the hope that they would stay. Then spake Sir Eckewart: “That may not be. We must fare further down to Rüdeger’s land. Many knights await us, for all wot well the news.”

Well wist fair Gotelind the tale. She tired her and her noble child with care. Rüdeger had sent her word that it thought him good that she should cheer the mind of the queen by riding forth, with his vassals to the Enns[3] for to meet her. When this message had been given, one saw on every side the roads alive; on foot and horse they hastened to meet their guests. Now was the queen come to Efferding.[4] Enow there were from the Bavarian land who might perchance have done the guests much harm, had they robbed upon the roads, as was their wont. That had been forestalled by the lordly margrave: he led a thousand knights or more.

Now Gotelind, the wife of Rüdeger, was come; with her there rode many a noble knight in lordly wise. When they were come across the Traun,[5] upon the plain by Enns, one saw erected huts and tents, where the guests should have their lodgings for the night. Rüdeger gave the vitaille to his guests. Fair Gotelind left her lodgings far behind her; along the road there trotted many a shapely palfrey with jingling bridle. Fair was the welcome; right well was Rüdeger pleased. Among those who rode to meet them on the way, on either side, in praiseworthy wise, was many a knight. They practised chivalry, the which full many a maiden saw. Nor did the service of the knights mislike the queen. When that Rüdeger’s liegemen met the guests, many truncheons[6] were seen to fly on high from the warriors’ hands in knightly custom. As though for a prize they rode before the ladies there. This they soon gave over and many warriors greeted each other in friendly wise. Then they escorted fair Gotelind from thence to where she saw Kriemhild. Scant leisure had they who wot how to serve the ladies.

The lord of Bechelaren rode now to his wife. Little it irked the noble margravine that he was come so well and sound from the Rhine. In part her cares had given way to joy. When she had welcomed him, he bade her dismount with the ladies of her train upon the sward. Many a noble knight bestirred him and served the ladies with eager zeal. Then Kriemhild spied the margravine standing with her meiny. No nearer she drew, but checked the palfrey with the bridle and bade them lift her quickly from the saddle. Men saw the bishop with Eckewart lead his sister’s child to Gotelind. All stood aside at once. Then the exiled queen kissed Gotelind upon the mouth. Full lovingly spake Rüdeger’s wife: “Now well is me, dear lady, that I have ever seen with mine own eyes your charming self in these our lands. Naught liefer might hap to me in all these times.”

“Now God requite you,” quoth Kriemhild, “most noble Gotelind. Shall I and Botelung’s[7] son remain alive and well, it may be lief to you that ye have seen me here.”

Neither knew what must needs later hap. Many maidens went to meet each other in courtly wise. The warriors, too, were full ready with their service. After the greeting they sat them down upon the clover. With many they became acquaint, who were full strange to them aforetime. As it was now high noon, men bade pour out wine for the ladies. The noble meiny no longer tarried, but rode to where they found many broad pavilions; there ample service stood ready for the guests.

That night they had repose till early on the morn. Those from Bechelaren made ready for to lodge the worthy guests. So well had Rüdeger planned, that little enow they lacked. The embrasures in the walls stood open, the castle at Bechelaren was opened wide. In rode the guests whom men were fain to see; the noble host bade purvey them proper easement. Most lovingly Rüdeger’s daughter with her meiny went to welcome the queen. There, too, stood her mother, the margrave’s wife; many a high-born maid was greeted with delight. They took each other by the hand and hied them hence to a broad hall, fashioned full fair, under which the Danube flowed along. Towards the breeze they sate and held great pastime. What more they did I cannot tell, save that Kriemhild’s men-at-arms were heard to grumble that they fared so slowly on their way, for much it irked them. Ho, what good knights rode with them hence from Bechelaren!

Rüdeger offered them much loving service. The queen gave Gotelind’s daughter twelve ruddy armlets, and raiment too, as good as any that she brought to Etzel’s land. Although the Nibelung gold was taken from her, yet she did win the hearts of all that saw her with the little she still might have. Great gifts were given to the courtiers of the host. In turn the Lady Gotelind offered the guests from the Rhine worship in such friendly wise, that men found passing few of the strangers that did not wear her jewels or her lordly robes.

When they had eaten and should depart, faithful service was proffered by the lady of the house to Etzel’s bride. The fair young margravine, too, was much caressed. To the queen she spake: “Whenso it thinketh you good, I know well that my dear father will gladly send me to you to the Hunnish land.” How well Kriemhild marked that the maiden loved her truly.

The steeds were harnessed and led before the castle of Bechelaren and the noble queen took leave of Rüdeger’s wife and daughter. With a greeting many a fair maid parted too. Full seldom did they see each other since these days. From Medelick[8] the folk bare in their hands many a rich cup of gold, in which they offered wine to the strangers on the highway. Thus they made them welcome. A host dwelt there, hight Astolt,[9] who showed them the road to the Austrian land, towards Mautern[10] down the Danube. There the noble queen was later served full well. From his niece the bishop parted lovingly. How he counseled her that she should bear her well and that she should purchase honor for herself, as Helca, too, had done! Ho, what great worship she later gained among the Huns!

To the Traisem[11] they escorted hence the guests. Rüdeger’s men purveyed them zealously, until the Huns came riding across the land. Then the queen became acquaint with mickle honor. Near the Traisem the king of the Hunnish land did have a mighty castle, hight Zeisenmauer,[12] known far and wide. Lady Helca dwelt there aforetime and used such great virtues that it might not lightly ever hap again, unless it be through Kriemhild. She wist so how to give, that after all her sorrow she had the joy that Etzel’s liegemen gave her great worship, of which she later won great store among the heroes. Etzel’s rule was known far and wide, so that all time one found at his court the boldest warriors of whom men ever heard, among Christian or among paynim. They were all come with him. All time there were at his court, what may not so lightly hap again, Christian customs and also heathen faith. In whatsoever wise each lived, the bounty of the king bestowed on all enow.

Adventure XXII. How Etzel Made Kriemhild His Bride

Until the fourth day she stayed at Zeisenmauer. The while the dust upon the highway never came to rest, but rose on every side, as if it were burning, where King Etzel’s liegemen rode through Austria. Then the king was told aright how royally Kriemhild fared through the lands; at thought of this his sorrows vanished. He hasted to where he found the lovely Kriemhild. Men saw ride before King Etzel on the road many bold knights of many tongues and many mighty troops of Christians and of paynims. When they met the lady, they rode along in lordly wise. Of the Russians and the Greeks there rode there many a man. The right good steeds of the Poles and Wallachians were seen to gallop swiftly, as they rode with might and main. Each did show the customs of his land. From the land of Kiev[1] there rode many a warrior and the savage Petschenegers.[2] With the bow they often shot at the birds which flew there; to the very head they drew the arrows on the bows.

By the Danube there lieth in the Austrian land a town that men call Tulna.[3] There she became acquaint with many a foreign custom, the which size had never seen afore. She greeted there enow who later came through her to grief. Before Etzel there rode a retinue, merry and noble, courtly and lusty, full four and twenty princes, mighty and of lofty birth. They would fain behold their lady and craved naught more. Duke Ramung[4] of Wallachia, with seven hundred vassals, galloped up before her; like flying birds men saw them ride. Then came Prince Gibeck with lordly bands. The doughty Hornbog,[5] with full a thousand men, wheeled from the king away towards the queen. Loudly they shouted after the custom of their land. Madly too rode the kinsmen of the Huns. Then came brave Hawart[6] of Denmark and the doughty Iring,[7] free of guile was he, and Irnfried[8] of Thuringia, a stately man. With twelve hundred vassals, whom they had in their band, they greeted Kriemhild, so that she had therefrom great worship. Then came Sir Bloedel,[9] King Etzel’s brother, from the Hunnish land, with three thousand men. In lordly wise he rode to where he found the queen. Then King Etzel came and Sir Dietrich, too, with all his fellowship. There stood many worshipful knights, noble, worthy, and good. At this Dame Kriemhild’s spirits rose.

Then Sir Rüdeger spake to the queen: “Lady, here will I receive the high-born king; whomso I bid you kiss, that must ye do. Forsooth ye may not greet alike King Etzel’s men.”

From the palfrey they helped the royal queen alight. Etzel, the mighty, bode no more, but dismounted from his steed with many a valiant man. Joyfully men saw them go towards Kriemhild. Two mighty princes, as we are told, walked by the lady and bore her train, when King Etzel went to meet her, where she greeted the noble lording with a kiss in gracious wise. She raised her veil and from out the gold beamed forth her rosy hue. Many a man stood there who vowed that Lady Helca could not have been more fair than she. Close by stood also Bloedel, the brother of the king. Him Rüdeger, the mighty margrave, bade her kiss and King Gibeck, too. There also stood Sir Dietrich. Twelve of the warriors the king’s bride kissed. She greeted many knights in other ways.

All the while that Etzel stood at Kriemhild’s side, the youthful warriors did as people still are wont to do. One saw them riding many a royal joust. This Christian champions did and paynim, too, according to their custom. In what right knightly wise the men of Dietrich made truncheons from the shafts fly through the air, high above the shields, from the hands of doughty knights! Many a buckler’s edge was pierced through and through by the German strangers. Great crashing of breaking shafts was heard. All the warriors from the land were come and the king’s guests, too, many a noble man.

Then the mighty king betook him hence with Lady Kriemhild. Hard by them a royal tent was seen to stand; around about the plain was filled with booths, where they should rest them after their toils. Many a comely maid was shown to her place thereunder by the knights, where she then sate with the queen on richly covered chairs. The margrave had so well purveyed the seats for Kriemhild, that all found them passing good; at this King Etzel grew blithe of mood. What the king there spake, I know not. In his right lay her snow-white hand; thus they sate in lover’s wise, since Rüdeger would not let the king make love to Kriemhild secretly.

Then one bade the tourney cease on every side; in courtly wise the great rout ended. Etzel’s men betook them to the booths; men gave them lodgings stretching far away on every side. The day had now an end; they lay at ease, till the bright morn was seen to dawn again, then many a man betook him to the steeds. Ho, what pastimes they gan ply in honor of the king! Etzel bade the Huns purvey all with fitting honors. Then they rode from Tulna to the town of Vienna, where they found many a dame adorned. With great worship these greeted King Etzel’s bride. There was ready for them in great plenty whatever they should have. Many a lusty hero rejoiced at prospect of the rout.

The king’s wedding feast commenced in merry wise. They began to lodge the guests, but quarters could not be found for all within the town. Rüdeger therefore begged those that were not guests to take lodgings in the country round about. I ween men found all time by Lady Kriemhild, Sir Dietrich and many another knight. Their rest they had given over for toil, that they might purvey the guests good cheer. Rüdeger and his friends had pastime good. The wedding feast fell on a Whitsuntide, when King Etzel lay by Kriemhild in the town of Vienna. With her first husband, I trow, she did not win so many men for service. Through presents she made her known to those who had never seen her. Full many among them spake to the guests: “We weened that Lady Kriemhild had naught of goods, now hath she wrought many wonders with her gifts.”

The feasting lasted seventeen days. I trow men can no longer tell of any king whose wedding feast was greater. If so be, ’tis hidden from us. All that were present wore brand-new garments. I ween, she never dwelt before in Netherland with such retinue of knights. Though Siegfried was rich in goods, I trow, he never won so many noble men-at-arms, as she saw stand ’fore Etzel. Nor hath any ever given at his own wedding feast so many costly mantles, long and wide, nor such good clothes, of which all had here great store, given for Kriemhild’s sake. Her friends and the strangers, too, were minded to spare no kind of goods. Whatever any craved, this they willingly gave, so that many of the knights through bounty stood bereft of clothes. Kriemhild thought of how she dwelt with her noble husband by the Rhine; her eyes grew moist, but she hid it full well, that none might see it. Great worship had been done her after many a grief. Whatever bounty any used, ’twas but a wind to that of Dietrich. What Botelung’s son had given him, was squandered quite. Rüdeger’s lavish hand did also many wonders. Prince Bloedel of Hungary bade empty many traveling chests of their silver and their gold; all this was given away. The king’s champions were seen to live right merrily. Werbel and Swemmel,[10] the minstrels of the king, each gained at the wedding feast, I ween, full thousand marks, or even better, when fair Kriemhild sate crowned at Etzel’s side.

On the eighteenth morning they rode forth from Vienna. Many shields were pierced in tilting by spears, which the warriors bare in hand. Thus King Etzel came down to the Hunnish land. They spent the night at ancient Heimburg.[11] No one might know the press of folk, or with what force they rode across the land. Ho, what fair women they found in Etzel’s native land! At mighty Misenburg[12] they boarded ship. The water which men saw flowing there was covered with steeds and men, as if it were solid earth. The wayworn ladies had their ease and rest. Many good ships were lashed together, that neither waves nor flood might do them harm. Upon them many a goodly tent was spread, as if they still had both land and plain.

From thence tidings came to Etzelburg,[13] at which both men and wives therein were glad. Helca’s meiny, that aforetime waited on their mistress, passed many a happy day thereafter at Kriemhild’s side. There many a noble maid stood waiting, who had great grief through Helca’s death. Kriemhild found still seven royal princesses there, through whom all Etzel’s land was graced. For the meiny the high-born maiden Herrat[14] cared, the daughter of Helca’s sister, beseen with many courtly virtues, the betrothed of Dietrich, a royal child, King Nentwin’s[15] daughter; much worship she later had. Blithe of heart she was at the coming of the guests; for this, too, mighty treasures were prepared. Who might tell the tale of how the king held court? Never had men lived better among the Huns with any queen.

When that the king with his wife rode from the shore, the noble Kriemhild was told full well who each one was; she greeted them the better. Ho, how royally she ruled in Helca’s stead! She became acquaint with much loyal service. Then the queen dealt out gold and vesture, silk and precious stones. Whatever she brought with her across the Rhine to Hungary must needs be given all away. All the king’s kinsmen and all his liegemen then owned her service, so that Lady Helca never ruled so mightily as she, whom they now must serve till Kriemhild’s death. The court and all the land lived in such high honors, that all time men found the pastimes which each heart desired, through the favor of the king and his good queen.

Endnotes

“Nibelungenlied,” the lay of the Nibelungs. The ordinary etymology of this name is ‘children of the mist’ (“Nebelkinder,” O. N. “Niflungar”), and it is thought to have belonged originally to the dwarfs. Piper, I, 50, interprets it as ‘the sons of Nibul’; Boer, II, 198, considers “Hniflungar” to be the correct Norse form and interprets it as ‘the descendants of Hnaef’ (O. E. “Hnaef,” O. H. G. “Hnabi”), whose death is related in the “Finnsaga.” ↩

“Adventure” (M. H. G. “aventiure,” from O. F. “aventure,” Lat. “adventura”). The word meant originally a happening, especially some great event, then the report of such an event. Here it is used in the sense of the different cantos or “fitts” of the poem, as in the “Gudrun” and other M. H. G. epics. Among the courtly poets it also frequently denotes the source, or is the personification of the muse of poetry. ↩

“Kriemhild” is the Upper German form of the Frankish “Grimhild.” In the MSS., the name generally appears with a further shifting as “Chriemhilt,” as if the initial consonant were Germanic “k.” On the various forms of the name, which have never yet been satisfactorily explained, see Mullenhoff, ZsfdA. xii, 299, 413; xv, 313; and Bohnenberger, PB. Beit. xxiv, 221–231. ↩

“Gunther” is the historical “Gundahari,” king of the Burgundians in the fifth century. ↩

“Gernot” was probably introduced by some minstrel in place of the historical “Godomar,” who appears in the Norse version as “Gutthormr,” though the names are not etymologically the same, as “Godomar” would be “Guthmarr” in Old Norse. ↩

“Giselher” is the historical “Gislaharius.” Although mentioned by the “Lex Burgundionum” as one of the Burgundian kings, he does not appear in the early Norse version, or in other poems dealing with these persons, such as the “Waltharius,” the “Rabenschlacht,” the “Rosengarten,” etc., and was probably introduced at a late date into the saga. Originally no rôle was ascribed to him, and not even his death is told. He probably came from some independent source. ↩

“Etzel” is the German form for the historical “Attila” (Norse “Atli”). A discussion of his connection with the saga will be found in the introduction. ↩

“Worms” is the ancient “Borbetomagus,” which in the first century BC was the chief city of the German tribe of the “Vangioni.” In the fifth century it was the capital of the Burgundian kingdom, but was destroyed by the Huns. The Merovingians rebuilt it, and in the seventh century it became a bishopric where Charlemagne at times held his court. It was later noted as the meeting-place of many imperial diets. It remained a free city till 1801. In the “Thidreksaga” the name is corrupted into “Wernize.” ↩

“Uta” (M. H. G. “Uote”). The name means ancestress, and is frequently used for the mother of heroes. The modern German form is “Ute,” but in order to insure its being pronounced with two syllables, the form “Uta” was chosen. ↩

“Dankrat” (M. H. G. “Dancrat”) appears as the father only in the “Nibelungenlied” and poems dependent on it, e.g., the “Klage” and “Biterolf,” elsewhere as “Gibiche” (Norse “Giuki”). ↩

“Hagen of Troneg.” Troneg is probably a corruption of the name of the Latin colony, “colonia Trajana,” on the Lower Rhine, which as early as the fifth century was written as “Troja,” giving rise to the legend that the Franks were descended from the ancient Trojans. “Troja” was then further corrupted to “Tronje” and “Tronege.” Hagen was therefore originally a Frank and had no connection with the Burgundian kings, as the lack of alliteration also goes to show. Boer thinks that not Siegfried but Hagen originally lived at Xanten (see note 3 to Adventure II), as this was often called Troja Francorum. When the Hagen story was connected with the Burgundians and Hagen became either their brother or their vassal, his home was transferred to Worms and Siegfried was located at Xanten, as he had no especial localization. Thus Siegfried is never called Siegfried of Troneg, as is Hagen. Other attempts to explain Troneg will be found in Piper, I, 48. ↩

“Dankwart” is not an historical character nor one that belonged to the early form of the legend. He may have come from another saga, where he played the principal rôle as Droege (ZsfdA. 48, 499) thinks. Boer considers him to be Hagen’s double, invented to play a part that would naturally fall to Hagen’s share, were he not otherwise engaged at the moment. In our poem he is called “Dancwart der snelle,” a word that has proved a stumbling-block to translators, because in modern German it means ‘speedy’, ‘swift’. Its original meaning was, however, ‘brave’, ‘warlike’, although the later meaning is already found in M. H. G. In all such doubtful cases the older meaning has been preferred, unless the context forbids, and the word ‘doughty’ has been chosen to translate it. ↩

“Ortwin of Metz” appears also in the “Eckenlied,” “Waltharius,” and in “Biterolf.” He is most likely a late introduction (but see Piper, I, 44). Rieger thinks that he belonged to a wealthy family “De Metis.” Though the “i” is long in the original, and Simrock uses the form “Ortewein” in his translation, the spelling with short “i” has been chosen, as the lack of accent tends to shorten the vowel in such names. ↩

“Gere” is likewise a late introduction. He is perhaps the historical Margrave Gere ↩

“Eckewart” is also a late accession. He is perhaps the historical margrave of Meissen ↩

“Folker of Alzei” (M. H. G. “Volker von Alzeije”), the knightly minstrel, is hardly an historical personage, in spite of the fact that Alzey is a well-known town in Rhine Hesse on the Selz, eighteen miles southwest of Mainz. The town has, to be sure, a violin in its coat of arms, as also the noble family of the same name. It is most likely, however, that this fact caused Folker to be connected with Alzei. In the “Thidreksaga” Folker did not play the rôle of minstrel, and it is probable that some minstrel reviser of our poem developed the character and made it the personification of himself. ↩

“Rumolt,” “Sindolt,” and “Hunolt” have no historical basis and merely help to swell the retinue of the Burgundians. ↩

“Worship.” This word has been frequently used here in its older meaning of ‘worth’, ‘reverence’, ‘respect’, to translate the M. H. G. “eren,” ‘honors’. ↩

“Siegmund” (M. H. G. “Sigemunt”) was originally the hero of an independent saga. See “Völsungasaga,” chaps. 3–8. ↩

“Siegelind” (M. H. G. “Sigelint”) is the correct name of Siegfried’s mother, as the alliteration shows. The Early Norse version has “Hjördis,” which has come from the “Helgi saga.” ↩

“Xanten” (M. H. G. “Santen” from the Latin “ad sanctos”) is at present a town in the Rhenish Prussian district of Düsseldorf. It does not now lie on the Rhine, but did in the Middle Ages. ↩

“Sword-thanes” (M. H. G. “swertdegene”) were the young squires who were to be made knights. It was the custom for a youthful prince to receive the accolade with a number of others. ↩

“Midsummer festival.” The M. H. G. “sunewende” means literally the ‘sun’s turning’, i.e., the summer solstice. This was one of the great Germanic festivals, which the church later turned into St. John’s Eve. The bonfires still burnt in Germany on this day are survivals of the old heathen custom. ↩

“Hurtling” translates here M. H. G. “buhurt,” a word borrowed from the French to denote a knightly sport in which many knights clashed together. Hurtling was used in older English in the same significance. ↩

“Palace” (M. H. G. “palas,” Lat. “palatium”) is a large building standing alone and largely used as a reception hall. ↩

“Truncheons” (M. H. G. “trunzûne,” O. F. “tronçon),” ‘lance splinters’, ‘fragments of spears’. ↩

“To-shivered,” ‘broken to pieces’, in imitation of the older English to-beat, to-break, etc. ↩

“Spangles” (M. H. G. “spangen”), strips of metal radiating from the raised centre of the shield and often set, as here, with precious stones. ↩

“Guest” translates here the M. H. G. “gest,” a word which may mean either ‘guest’ or ‘stranger,’ and it is often difficult, as here, to tell to which meaning the preference should be given. ↩

“Eleven” translates the M. H. G. “selbe zwelfte,” which means one of twelve. The accounts are, however, contradictory, as a few lines below mention is made of twelve companions of Siegfried. ↩

“Vair” (O. F. “vair,” Lat. “varius”), ‘variegated’, like the fur of the squirrel. ↩

“Known.” It was a mark of the experienced warrior, that he was acquainted with the customs and dress of various countries and with the names and lineage of all important personages. Thus in the “Hildebrandslied” Hildebrand asks Hadubrand to tell him his father’s name, and adds: “If thou tellest me the one, I shall know the other.” ↩

“Schilbung” and “Nibelung,” here spoken of as the sons of a mighty king, were originally dwarfs, and, according to some authorities, the original owners of the treasure. Boer, ix, 199, thinks, however, that the name Nibelungs was transferred from Hagen to these dwarfs at a late stage in the formation of the saga. ↩

“Angry of mood.” The reason of this anger is apparent from the more detailed account in “Biterolf,” 7801. The quarrel arose from the fact that, according to ancient law, Siegfried acquired with the sword the rights of the first born, which the brothers, however, refused to accord to him. ↩

“Balmung.” In the older Norse version and in the “Thidreksaga” Siegfried’s sword bore the name of Gram. ↩

“Alberich” is a dwarf king who appears in a number of legends, e.g., in the “Ortnit saga” and in “Biterolf.” Under the Romance form of his name, “Oberon,” he plays an important rôle in modern literature. ↩

“Cloak of Darkness.” This translates the M. H. G. “tarnkappe,” a word often retained by translators. It is formed from O. H. G. tarni, ‘secret’ (cf. O. E. “dyrne”), and “kappe” from late Latin “cappa,” ‘cloak’. It rendered the wearer invisible and gave him the strength of twelve men. ↩

“Saxons.” This war with the Saxons does not appear in the poetic “Edda,” but was probably introduced into the story later to provide the heroes with a suitable activity in the period elapsing between Siegfried’s marriage and the journey to Brunhild’s land. (In our poem it is placed before the marriage.) It reflects the ancient feuds between the Franks on the one hand and the Saxons and Danes on the other. Originally Siegfried probably did not take part in it, but was later introduced and made the leader of the expedition in place of the king, in accordance with the tendency to idealize him and to give him everywhere the most important rôle. The two opposing leaders are “Liudeger,” lord of the Saxons, and “Liudegast,” king of Denmark. In “Biterolf” Liudeger rules over both Saxons and Danes, and Liudegast is his brother. ↩

“Fey.” This Scotch and older English word has been chosen to translate the M. H. G. “veige,” ‘fated’, ‘doomed’, as it is etymologically the same word. The ancient Germans were fatalists and believed only those would die in battle whom fate had so predestined. ↩

“Thirty thousand.” The M. H. G. epics are fond of round numbers and especially of thirty and its multiples. They will be found to occur very frequently in our poem. See Lachmann, “Anmerkungen zu den Nibelungen,” 474 1. ↩

“Their.” The original is obscure here; the meaning is, ‘when he heard with what message they were come, he rued the haughtiness of the Burgundians’. ↩

“Marks of gold.” A mark (Lat. “mares”) was half a pound of gold or silver. ↩

“Fillets” were worn only by married women. ↩

“Ferran,” a gray colored cloth of silk and wool; from O. F. “ferrandine.” ↩

“Clasps” or “brooches” were used to fasten the dresses in front. ↩

“Isenland” translates here M. H. G. “Islant,” which has, however, no connection with Iceland in spite of the agreement of the names in German. Îsen lant, the reading of the MSS. BJh, has been chosen, partly to avoid confusion, and partly to indicate its probable derivation from “Îsenstein,” the name of Brunhild’s castle. Boer’s interpretation of “Isen” as ‘ice’ finds corroboration in Otfrid’s form “isine steina” (‘ice stones’, i.e. crystals) I, 1. 70. Îsenstein would then mean Ice Castle. In the “Thidreksaga” Brunhild’s castle is called “Saegarthr” (‘Sea Garden’), and in a fairy tale (No. 93 of Grimm) “Stromberg,” referring to the fact that it was surrounded by the sea. Here, too, in our poem it stands directly on the shore. ↩

“Zazamanc,” a fictitious kingdom mentioned only here and a few times in Parzival, Wolfram probably having obtained the name from this passage. (See Bartsch, “Germanistische Studien,” ii, 129.) ↩

“Wont to wear.” In the Middle Ages costly furs and fish-skins were used as linings and covered, as here described, with silk or cloth. By fish such amphibious animals as otter and beaver were often meant. ↩

“Well fit.” In this passage “wert,” the reading of A and D, has been followed, instead of unwert of B and C, as it seems more appropriate to the sense. ↩

“Dight,” ‘arrayed’; used by Milton. ↩

“Brunhild.” The following words are evidently a late interpolation, and weaken the ending, but have been translated for the sake of completeness. They are spoken by Siegfried. ↩

“Palaces.” See Adventure III, note 7. ↩

“Surcoat,” which here translates the M. H. G. “wafenhemde,” is a light garment of cloth or silk worn above the armor. ↩

“Azagouc.” See Zazamanc, Adventure VI, note 2. This strophe is evidently a late interpolation, as it contradicts the description given above. ↩

Weights. The M. H. G. “messe” (Lat. “massa”) is just as indefinite as the English expression. It was a mass or lump of any metal, probably determined by the size of the melting-pot. ↩

Adventure VIII. This whole episode, in which Siegfried fetches men to aid Gunther in case of attempted treachery on Brunhild’s part, is of late origin and has no counterpart in the older versions. It is a further development of Siegfried’s fight in which he slew Schilbung and Nibelung and became the ruler of the Nibelung land. The fight with Alberich is simply a repetition of the one in the former episode. ↩

“Rest” (M. H. G. “rast”), originally ‘repose’, then used as a measure of distance, as here. ↩

“Knobs,” round pieces of metal fastened to the scourge. ↩

“Cunning” is to be taken here in the Biblical sense of ‘knowing’. The M. H. G. “listig” which it here translates, denotes ‘skilled’ or ‘learned’ in various arts and is a standing epithet of dwarfs. ↩

“Mulled wine” translates M. H. G. “lutertranc,” a claret mulled with herbs and spice and left to stand until clear. ↩

“Mark.” See Adventure V, note 5. ↩

“Chaplet” (O. F. “chaplet,” dim. of “chapel,” M. H. G. “schapel” or “schapelin”) or wreath was the headdress especially of unmarried girls, the hair being worn flowing. It was often of flowers or leaves, but not infrequently of gold and silver. (See Weinhold, “Deutsche Frauen im Mittelalter,” i, 387.) ↩

“Eckewart,” see Adventure I, note 15. ↩

“Xanten,” see Adventure II, note 3. ↩

“Cognizance,” ‘jurisdiction.’ ↩

“Dames,” i.e., Siegelind and Kriemhild. ↩

“Norway.” The interpolated character of the Adventures XI to XIII, which are not found in the earlier versions, is shown by the confusion in the location of Siegfried’s court. The poet has forgotten that Xanten is his capital, and locates it in Norway. No mention is made, however, of the messengers crossing the sea; on the contrary, Kriemhild speaks of their being sent down the Rhine. ↩

“Meiny” (M. E. “meiny,” O. F. “mesnee”), ‘courtiers’, ‘serving folk’. ↩

“Housings,” ‘saddle cloths’. ↩

“Leman” (M. E. “lemman,” O. E. “leof mann,” ‘lief man’, i.e., ‘dear one’), ‘mistress’ in a bad sense. ↩

“Marriage morning gift” was the gift which it was customary for the bridegroom to give the bride on the morning after the bridal night. On this custom see Weinhold, “Deutsche Frauen im Mittelalter,” i, p. 402. ↩

“Alberich,” see Adventure III, note 8. It is characteristic of the poem that even this dwarf is turned into a knight. ↩

“Wishing-rod,” a magic device for discovering buried treasure. Cf. Grimm, “Deutsche Mythologie,” ii, 813. ↩

“Loche,” according to Piper, is the modern “Locheim” in the Rhine province. ↩

“Brach,” ‘hunting dog’, cognate with M. H. G. “bracke,” used here. ↩

“Lion.” It is hardly necessary to state that lions did not roam at large in the forests of Germany. They were, however, frequently exhibited in the Middle Ages, and the poet introduced one here to enhance Siegfried’s fame as a hunter. ↩

“Ure-oxen,” the auerochs, or European bison, now practically extinct. ↩

“Shelk” (M. H. G. “schelch”), probably a species of giant deer. ↩

“Fragrance.” It was believed that the odor of the panther attracted the game. Compare the description of the panther in the older “Physiologus,” where the odor is said to surpass that of all ointments. ↩

“Otter” translates here M. H. G. “ludem,” whose exact connotation is not known. Some interpret it to meau the fish otter, others the “Waldschrat,” a kind of faun. ↩

“Balmung,” see Adventure III, note 7. ↩

“Spessart wood” lies forty to fifty miles east of Worms and is therefore too distant for a day’s hunt, but such trifles did not disturb the poet. ↩

“Mulled wine,” see Adventure VIII, note 5. ↩

“Feet.” This was probably done as a handicap. The time consumed in rising to his feet would give his opponent quite a start. ↩

“Bleed.” This was not only a popular superstition, but also a legal practice in case of a murder when the criminal had not been discovered, or if any one was suspected. The suspected person was requested to approach the bier and touch the body, in the belief that the blood would flow afresh if the one touching the body were guilty. Our passage is the first instance of its mention in German literature. A similar one occurs in “Iwein,” 1355–1364. The usage was also known in France and England. See the instances quoted by Jacob Grimm in his “Rechtsaltertumer,” 930. ↩

“Etzel,” see Adventure I, note 7. ↩

“Helca” (M. H. G. “Helche”) or “Herka,” Etzel’s wife, is the daughter of king “Oserich” or “Osantrix,” as the “Thidreksaga” calls him. In the latter work (chap. 73–80) we read how Rüdeger (Rodingeir) took her by force from her father and brought her to Etzel to be the latter’s bride. On her identity with the historical “Kerka” of Priscus, see Bleyer, PB. “Beit.” xxxi, 542. ↩

“Rüdeger of Bechelaren,” or, as the name reads in the “Thidreksaga,” “Rodingeir of Bakalar,” is probably not an historical personage, but the hero of a separate legend. Evidence of this is seen in the fact that he calls himself an exile, though he is Etzel’s mightiest vassal, with castles and lands in fief. He may have been introduced, as Wilmanns (“Anz.” xviii 101) thinks, to play a rôle originally assigned to Dietrich, who is also an exile. Mullenhoff considered him to have been a mythical person. Bechelaren, or Pechlarn, lies at the junction of the Erlach with the Danube. ↩

“hast seen here.” “Biterolf,” 9471, relates that Dietrich had carried Siegfried, when young, by force to Etzel’s court. ↩

“full soon.” See Adventure III, note 4. ↩

“Paynim” (O F. “paienime,” late Latin “paganismus”), ‘heathen’. ↩

“gold for offerings.” This was the gold to be used as offering when masses were sung for Siegfried’s soul. ↩

“Vergen” is the modern Pföring, below Ingolstadt. A ferry across the river existed here from ancient times. ↩

“Pilgrim,” or “Pilgerin,” as he is variously called, is an historical personage. He was bishop of Passau from 971 to 991. Without doubt he is a late introduction, according to Boer between 1181 and 1185. See Boer, ii, 204, and E. L. Dummler, “Pilgrim von Passau,” Leipzig, 1854. ↩

“Enns” (M. H. G. “Ens”) is one of the tributaries of the Danube, flowing into it about eleven miles southeast of Linz. ↩

“Efferding” (M. H. G. “Everdingen”) is a town on the Danube, about thirteen miles west of Linz. ↩

“Traun” (M. H. G. “Trune”) is a river of Upper Austria, forty-four miles southeast of Linz. ↩

“Truncheons,” see Adventure II, note 8. ↩

“Botelung’s son” is Attila, who is so called in our poem, in the “Klage,” and in “Biterolf.” In the earlier Norse version “Atli” is the son of “Budli.” (On this point see Mullenhoff, “Zur Geschichte der Nibelungensage,” p. 106, and Zsfd A., x, 161, and Bleyer, PB. Beit. xxxi, 459, where the names are shown to be identical.) ↩

“Medelick” is the modern Mölk, or Melk, a town on the Danube near the influx of the Bilach. It lies at the foot of a granite cliff on which stands a famous Benedictine abbey. ↩

“Astolt” appears only in this passage; nothing else is known of him. ↩

“Mautern” is situated at the influx of the Flanitz, opposite Stein in Lower Austria. ↩

“Traisem,” Traisen, is a tributary of the Danube in Lower Austria, emptying near Traismauer. ↩

“Zeisenmauer” (M. H. G. “Zeizenmure”). All the MSS. but C and D have this reading. The latter have “Treysenmoure” and “treisem moure,” which corresponds better to the modern name, as Zeiselmauer lies between Tulln and Vienna. It is possible, however, that the town on the Traisem was originally called Zeiselmauer, as the road leading from Traismauer to Tulln still bears the name of Zeiselstrasse. See Lachmann, “Anmerkungen,” 1272, 3, and Piper, ii, 289, note to str. 1333. ↩

“Kiev” (M. H. G. “Kiew”) is now a government in the southwestern part of Russia. Its capital of the same name, situated on the Dnieper, is the oldest of the better known cities of Russia, and in the latter Middle Ages was an important station of the Hanseatic league. ↩

“Petschenegers,” a Turkish tribe originally dwelling to the north of the Caspian. By conquest they acquired a kingdom extending from the Don to Transylvania. They were feared for their ferociousness and because they continually invaded the surrounding countries, especially Kiev. ↩

“Tulna” (M. H. G. “Tulne”) is the modern Tulln, a walled town of Lower Austria, seventeen miles northwest of Vienna on the Danube. ↩

“Ramung and Gibeck” (M. H. G. “Gibeche”) appear only in our poem, nothing else is known of them. ↩

“Hornbog” is frequently mentioned in the “Thidreksaga,” but nothing otherwise is known of him. ↩

“Hawart” is perhaps identical with the Saxon duke Hadugot, who is reputed to have played an important part in the conquest of Thuringia. He evidently comes from the Low German version. ↩

“Iring” is considered by Wilmanns to have been originally an ancient deity, as the Milky Way is called Iringe strâze or “Iringi.” He occurs in a legend of the fall of the Thuringian kingdom, where he played such a prominent rôle that the Milky Way was named after him. See W. Grimm, “Heldensage,” p. 394, who thinks, however, that the connection of Iring with the Milky Way is the result of a confusion. ↩

“Irnfried” is considered to be Hermanfrid of Thuringia, who was overthrown and killed in AD 535 by Theuderich with the aid of the Saxons. See Felix Dahn, “Urgeschichte,” iii, 73–79. He, too, comes from the Low German tradition. ↩

“Bloedel” is Bleda, the brother of Attila, with whom he reigned conjointly from AD 433 to 445. In our poem the name appears frequently with the diminutive ending, as “Bloedelin.” ↩

“Werbel and Swemmel,” who doubtless owe their introduction to some minstrel, enjoy special favor and are intrusted with the important mission of inviting the Burgundians to Etzel’s court, an honor that would hardly be accorded to persons of their rank. Swemmel appears mostly in the diminutive form “Swemmelin.” ↩

“Heimburg” lies on the Danube near the Hungarian border. ↩

“Misenburg” is the modern Wieselburg on the Danube, twenty-one miles southeast of Pressburg. ↩

“Etzelburg” was later identified with the old part of Budapest, called in German “Ofen,” through the influence of Hungarish legends, but, as G. Heinrich has shown, had no definite localization in the older M. H. G. epics. See Bleyer, PB. Belt. xxxi 433 and 506. The name occurs in documents as late as the fifteenth century. ↩

“Herrat,” the daughter of King “Nentwin” is frequently mentioned in the “Thidreksaga” as Dietrich’s betrothed. She is spoken of as the exiled maid. ↩

“Nentwin” is not found in any other saga, and nothing else is known of him. See W. Grimm, “Heldensage,” 103. ↩

“Ortlieb” is not historical, and in the “Thidreksaga” Etzel’s son is called Aldrian. Bleyer, “Die germanischen Elemente der ungarischen, Hunnensage,” PB. Beit. xxxi, 570, attempt to prove the identity of the names by means of a form “Arda,” giving on the one hand Hungarian “Aladar,” “Aldrian,” on the other German “Arte,” “Orte.” ↩

“Hungary.” According to the account in “Waltharius,” Hagen spent his youth as a hostage at Etzel’s court. ↩

“Hostage,” i.e., he has never betrayed you to your enemies. ↩

“Gran,” royal free city of Hungary, on the right bank of the Danube opposite the influx of the Gran, twenty-four miles northwest of Budapest. ↩

“Scathful scathe” here imitates the M. H. G. “scaden scedelich.” ↩

“Balmung,” see Adventure III, note 7. ↩

“friend … friendly.” This repetition occurs in the original. ↩

“Irnfried,” see Adventure XXII, note 8. ↩

“Hawart” and “Iring,” Adventure XXII, notes 6 and 7. ↩

“Morat” (M. H. G. “moraz”) from late Latin “moratum,” mulberry wine, is a beverage composed of honey flavored with mulberry-juice. ↩

“a thousand and sixty.” This does not agree with the account in Adventure XXIV, where we read of a thousand of Hagen’s men, eighty of Dankwart’s, and thirty of Folker’s. The nine thousand foot soldiers mentioned here are a later interpolation, as the “Thidreksaga” speaks of only a thousand all told. ↩

“Eastern Frankland,” or East Franconia, is the ancient province of “Franconia Orientalis,” the region to the east of the Spessart forest, including the towns of Fulda, Würzburg and Barnberg. In Biterolf Dietlieb journeys through Eastern Frankland to the Danube. ↩

“Swanfield” (M. H. G. “Swanevelde”) is the ancient province of “Sualafeld” between the Rezat and the Danube. ↩

“Gelfrat” is a Bavarian lord and the brother of “Else,” mentioned below. Their father’s name was also Else. ↩

“Wise women,” a generic name for all supernatural women of German mythology. While it is not specifically mentioned, it is probable that the wise women, or mermaids, as they are also called here, were ‘swan maidens’, which play an important rôle in many legends and are endowed with the gift of prophecy. They appear in the form of swans, and the strange attire of the wise women mentioned here refers to the so-called swan clothes which they wore and which enabled Hagen to recognize them as supernatural beings. On bathing they lay aside this garment, and he who obtains possession of it has them in his power. This explains their eagerness to give Hagen information, if he will return their garments to them. For an account of them see Grimm’s “Mythologie,” 355. ↩

“Aldrian” is not an historical personage; the name is merely a derivative of “aldiro,” ‘the elder’, and signifies ‘ancestor’, just as Uta means ‘ancestress’. In the “Thidreksaga” Aldrian is the king of the Nibelung land and the father of Gunther, Giselher, and Gernot, whereas Hagen is the son of an elf by the same mother. ↩

Else appears also in “Biterolf”; in the “Thidreksaga” he is called “Elsung,” the younger, as his father bore the same name. See Adventure XXV, note 4. ↩

“Amelrich” is the ferryman’s brother. ↩

“Spear.” It was the custom to offer presents on a spear point, perhaps to prevent the recipient from treacherously using his sword. Compare the similar description in the “Hildebrandslied,” 37, where we are told that gifts should be received with the spear. ↩

“Goods.” In the “Thidreksaga” the ferryman desires the ring for his young wife, which explains better the allusion to marriage and the desire for wealth. ↩

“To-broke,” see Adventure II, note 9. ↩

“Clerk,” ‘priest’. ↩

“Adventure XXVI.” This adventure is a late interpolation, as it is not found in the “Thidreksaga.” Originally the river must be thought of as separating them from Etzel’s kingdom. ↩

“Moering” (M. H. G. “Moeringen”) lies between Pföring and Ingolstadt. In the “Thidreksaga” we are told that the mermaids were bathing in a body of water called “Moere,” whereas in our poem they bathe in a spring. This may be the original form of the account and the form here contaminated. See Boer, i, 134. ↩

“Eckewart,” see Adventure I, note 15. It will be remembered that he accompanied Kriemhild first to the Netherlands, then stayed with her at Worms after Siegfried’s death, and finally journeyed with her to Etzel’s court. Originally he must be thought of as guarding the boundary of Etzel’s land. Without doubt he originally warned the Burgundians, as in the early Norse versions, where Kriemhild fights on the side of her brothers, but since this duty was given to Dietrich, he has nothing to do but to announce their arrival to Rüdeger. His sleeping here may, however, be thought to indicate that it was too late to warn Gunther and his men. ↩

“Chaplets,” see Adventure 10, note 1. ↩

“Of yore,” see Adventure 23, note 2. ↩

“Nudung” was slain, according to the “Thidreksaga,” chap. 335, by “Vidga” (here Wittich, M. H. G. “Witege,” the son of Wielant, the smith, in the battle of Gronsport. There, chap. 369, he is Gotelind’s brother, but in “Biterolf” and the “Rosengarten” he is her son. ↩

“Marks,” see Adventure V, note 5. ↩

“Hildebrand” is the teacher and armor bearer of Dietrich. He is the hero of the famous “Hildebrandslied.” ↩

“Wolfhart” is Hildebrand’s nephew. In the “Thidreksaga” he falls in the battle of Gronsport. ↩

“Amelung land” is the name under which Dietrich’s land appears. Theodorich, the king of the East Goths, belonged to the race of the Amali. ↩

“Feast.” That Kriemhild kissed only Giselher, who was innocent of Siegfried’s death, aroused Hagen’s suspicions. ↩

“Vassal.” No other account speaks of Aldrian as being at Etzel’s court. He is probably confused here with his son, for Hagen’s stay with Etzel in various legends, as also in our poem a few lines further down. ↩

“Walther of Spain” is Walther of Aquitania, a legendary personage of whom the O. E. fragment “Waldere,” the Latin epic “Waltharius,” a M. H. G. epic, and the “Thidreksaga” tell. He flees with Hildegund, the daughter of the Burgundian King Herrich, from Etzel’s court, as related here, but has to fight for his life against overpowering numbers, in the “Thidreksaga” against the pursuing Huns, in the other sources against the Burgundians. In both cases Hagen is among his foes, but takes no part in the fight at first, out of friendship for Walther. ↩

“Arras,” the capital of Artois in the French Netherlands. In older English “arras” is used also for tapestry. ↩

“Adventure XXXI.” This adventure is of late origin, being found only in our poem. See the introduction. ↩

“Truncheons,” see Adventure II, note 8. ↩

“Schrutan.” This name does not occur elsewhere. Piper suggests, that perhaps a Scotchman is meant, as “Skorottan” appears in the “Thidreksaga,” chap. 28, as an ancient name of Scotland. ↩

“Gibecke,” “Ramung” and “Hornbog,” see Adventure XXII, notes 4 and 5. ↩

“Nudung,” see Adventure XXVII, note 3. ↩

“Ortlieb.” In the “Thidreksaga” Etzel’s son is called Aldrian. There, however, he is killed because he strikes Hagen in the face, here in revenge for the killing of the Burgundian footmen. ↩

“Fey,” see Adventure V, note 2. ↩

Adventure XXXII. The details of the following scenes differ materially in the various sources. A comparative study of them will be found in the works of Wilmanns and Boer. ↩

“Marriage morning gift” (M. H. G. “morgengabe”) was given by the bridegroom to the bride on the morning after the wedding. See Adventure XIX, note 1. ↩

“Aldrian’s son,” i.e., Dankwart. ↩

“Sewers” (O. F. “asseour,” M. L. “adsessor” ‘one who sets the table’; cf. F. “asseoir” ‘to set’, ‘place’, Lat. “ad sedere”), older English for an upper servant who brought on and removed the dishes from the table. ↩

“Friendship” translates the M. H. G. “minne trinken” ‘to drink to the memory of a person’, an old custom originating with the idea of pouring out a libation to the gods. Later it assumed the form of drinking to the honor of God, of a saint, or of an absent friend. See Grimm, “Mythologie,” p. 48. ↩

“Amelungs,” see Adventure XXVIII, note 3. ↩

“Wolfhart,” see Adventure XXVIII, note 2. ↩

“Gauds,” ornaments. ↩

“Waskstone,” see Adventure XXXV, note 2. ↩

“Fall.” The word “not,” translated here “fall,” means really ‘disaster’, but as this word is not in keeping with the style, “fall” has been chosen as preferable to ‘need’, used by some translators. The MS. C has here “liet” instead of “not” of A and B. ↩

The “Nibelungenlied” is continued by the so-called “Klage,” a poem written in short rhyming couplets. As the name indicates, it describes the lamentations of the survivors over the dead. The praises of each warrior are sung and a messenger dispatched to acquaint Gotelind, Uta, and Brunhild with the sad end of their kinsmen. It closes with Dietrich’s departure from Etzel’s court and his return home. Although in one sense a continuation of our poem, the “Klage” is an independent work of no great merit, being excessively tedious with its constant repetitions. A reprint and a full account of it will be found in Piper’s edition of our poem, vol. I. ↩

“Weregild” (O. E. “wer,” ‘a man’, “gild,” ‘payment of money’), legal term for compensation paid for a man killed. ↩

“Waska.” In “Biterolf” it is the name of the sword of Walther of Wasgenstein and is connected with the old German name, “Wasgenwald,” for the Vosges. ↩

“Parlous,” older English for ‘perilous’. ↩

“Fey,” ‘doomed to death’, here in the sense of ‘already slain’. See Adventure V, note 2. ↩

“Strangers,” i.e., those who are sojourning there far from home. ↩

“Helfrich” appears also in the “Thidreksaga,” chap. 330, where we are told that he was the bravest and courtliest of all knights. ↩

“Master Hildebrand,” see Adventure XXVIII, note 1. ↩

“Siegstab” is Dietrich’s nephew. He also appears in the “Thidreksaga,” but in a different rôle. ↩

“Wolfwin” is mentioned in the “Klage,” 1541, as Dietrich’s nephew. ↩

“Wolfbrand” and “Helmnot” appear only here. ↩

“Ritschart.” With the exception of Helfrich (see Above note 1), these names do not occur elsewhere, though one of the sons of Haimon was called Wichart. ↩

A is a parchment MS. of the second half of the thirteenth century, now found in Munich. It forms the basis of Lachmann’s edition. It is a parchment MS. of the middle of the thirteenth century, belonging to the monastery of St. Gall. It has been edited by Bartsch, “Deutsche Klassiker des Mittelalters,” vol. 3, and by Piper, “Deutsche National-Literatur,” vol. 6. C is a parchment MS., of the thirteenth century, now in the ducal library of Donauesehingen. It is the best written of all the MSS., and has been edited by Zarncke. ↩

The “Thidreksaga” differs from the other Norse versions in having “Sigfrod,” as he is called here, brought up in ignorance of his parents, a trait which was probably borrowed from the widespread “Genoveva” story, although thought by some to have been an original feature of our legend. ↩

The “Thidreksaga,” which has forgotten the enmity of the brothers, and calls Sigurd’s tutor “Mimr,” tells the episode in somewhat different fashion. The brothers plan to kill Sigurd, and the latter is attacked by the dragon, while burning charcoal in the forest. After killing the monster with a firebrand, Sigurd bathes himself in the blood and thus become covered with a horny skin, which renders him invulnerable, save in one place between the shoulder blades, which he could not reach. This bathing in the blood is also related in the Seyfrid ballad and in the “Nibelungenlied,” with the difference, that the vulnerable spot is caused by a linden leaf falling upon him. ↩

The fact that all but one of these names alliterate, shows that the Norse version is here more original. Gunnar is the same as Gunther (Gundaharius), Högni as Hagen; Gutthorm (Godomar) appears in the German version as Gernot. In this latter the father is called Dancrat, the mother Uote, and the name Grimhild is transferred from the mother to the daughter. ↩

In the prose “Edda,” in the water which drips from Gudrun’s hair. ↩